January 17, 2024 University of Waterloo, Ontario, Canada nilslukas.github.io / nlukas@uwaterloo.ca

Research Overview

My research focuses on Trustworthy Machine Learning (ML) and threats that emerge when providing large ML systems to many users. These threats include (i) untrustworthy data that was manipulated to undermine the model's **reliability**, (ii) untrustworthy models that lack **privacy** and inadvertently disclose training data to unauthorized users, and (iii) untrustworthy users who **misuse** the model's generated content to erode trust in digital media. To mitigate these threats, I study defenses against data poisoning, differential privacy, and watermarking for generative ML systems to detect generated content.

Education

Ph.D. in Computer Science, University of Waterloo, Canada	Jan 2019 - Feb 2024
Advisor: Prof. Florian Kerschbaum	
Thesis: "Analyzing Threats of Large-Scale Machine Learning Systems"	
M.Sc. in Computer Science, RWTH-Aachen, Germany	May 2016 - Oct 2018
Advisor: Prof. Stefan Decker	
Thesis: "Secure Inference of Deep Neural Networks"	
B.Sc. in Computer Science, RWTH-Aachen, Germany	Oct 2012 - Apr 2016

Experience

Research Intern, Microsoft Research	May 2022 - Aug 2022
Topic: Privacy for Large Language Models (see our S&P'23 publication).	
Instructional Advisor, University of Waterloo	Sep 2021 - Dec 2021
Course: Object-Oriented Software Development	
Co-Instructor, Group on Information Systems at the RWTH-Aachen	Oct 2017 - Mar 2018
Course: Data-Driven Medicine	

Conference Publications

[ICLR'24]

AR: 30.8% (2250/7262)

[ICLR'24]

[USENIX'23]

AR: 29.2% (422/1444)

[IEEE S&P'23]

AR: 17.0% (195/1147)

₱ Distinguished Contribution Award at Microsoft MLADS

[IEEE S&P'22]

AR: 14.5% (147/1012)

[ICLR'21]

AR: 28.7% (860/2997)

Spotlight (Notable 5%)

[IH&MMSEC'21]

AR: 40.0% (128/318)

Nils Lukas, Abdulrahman Diaa, Lucas Fenaux, Florian Kerschbaum. *Leveraging Optimization for Adaptive Attacks on Image Watermarks*. The Twelfth International Conference on Learning Representations, 2024 [pdf]

Benjamin Schneider, **Nils Lukas**, Florian Kerschbaum. *Universal Backdoor Attacks*. The Twelfth International Conference on Learning Representations, 2024, [pdf] [news].

Nils Lukas and Florian Kerschbaum. PTW: Pivotal Tuning Watermarking for Pre-Trained Image Generators, 32nd USENIX Security Symposium, 2023, [pdf]
Nils Lukas Ahmed Salem Robert Sim Shruti Tople Lukas Wutschitz Santiago

Nils Lukas, Ahmed Salem, Robert Sim, Shruti Tople, Lukas Wutschitz, Santiago Zanella-Béguelin. *Analyzing Leakage of Personally Identifiable Information in Language Models*, 44th IEEE Symposium on Security and Privacy, 2023, [pdf]

Nils Lukas, Edward Jiang, Xinda Li, Florian Kerschbaum. *SoK: How Robust is Image Classification Deep Neural Network Watermarking?*, 43rd IEEE Symposium on Security and Privacy, 2022, [pdf]

Nils Lukas, Yuxuan Zhang, Florian Kerschbaum. *Deep Neural Network Finger-printing by Conferrable Adversarial Examples*, The Ninth International Conference on Learning Representations, 2021 [pdf]

Masoumeh Shafieinejad, **Nils Lukas**, Jiaqi Wang, Xinda Li, Florian Kerschbaum. *On the Robustness of Backdoor-based Watermarking in Deep Neural Networks*, Proceedings of the 2021 ACM Workshop on Information Hiding and Multimedia Security, 2021, [pdf]

[ACSAC'20]

AR: 20.9% (104/497)

Rasoul Mahdavi, Thomas Humphries, Bailey Kacsmar, Simeon Krastnikov, **Nils Lukas**, John Premkumar, Masoumeh Shafieinejad, Simon Oya, Florian Kerschbaum, Erik-Oliver Blass. *Practical Over-Threshold Multi-Party Private Set Intersection*, Annual Computer Security Applications Conference, 2020, [pdf] Bailey Kacsmar, Basit Khurram, **Nils Lukas**, Alexander Norton, Masoumeh Shafieinejad, Zhiwei Shang, Yaser Baseri, Maryam Sepehri, Simon Oya, Florian Kerschbaum. *Differentially private two-party set operations*, 2020 IEEE European Symposium on Security and Privacy (EuroS&P), 2020, [pdf]

[IEEE EuroS&P'20]

AR: 20.9% (39/187)

Journal Publications

[AIP'18]

Pascal Richter, Gregor Heiming, **Nils Lukas**, Martin Frank. *SunFlower: A new Solar Tower Simulation Method for use in Field Layout Optimization*, AIP Conference Proceedings, Volume 2033, Issue 1, 2018, [pdf]

Working Papers

2023	Nils Lukas, Florian Kerschbaum. Pick your Poison: Undetectability versus Robustness in
	Data Poisoning Attacks against Deep Image Classification, 2023, [pdf]
2023	Rasoul Mahdavi, Nils Lukas , Faezeh Ebrahimianghazani, Thomas Humphries, Bailey Kacsmar, John Premkumar, Xinda Li, Simon Oya, Ehsan Amjadian, Florian Kerschbaum. <i>PEPSI: Practically Efficient Private Set Intersection in the Unbalanced Setting</i> , 2023, [pdf]
2023	Abdulrahman Diaa, Lucas Fenaux, Thomas Humphries, Marian Dietz, Faezeh Ebrahimianghazani, Bailey Kacsmar, Xinda Li, Nils Lukas , Rasoul Akhavan Mahdavi, Simon Oya, Ehsan Amjadian, Florian Kerschbaum. <i>Fast and Private Inference of Deep Neural Networks by Co-designing Activation Functions</i> , 2023, [pdf]

Tutorials

[ESWC'18]

Nils Lukas, Oya Beyan, Ali Hasnain. *Privacy-Preserving Information Extraction with Bloom Filters*, European Semantic Web Conference, Greece, 2018, [web]

Awards and Honors

2023	Best Poster Award - Presentation with David R. Cheriton [300 CAD]
	Distinguished Contribution Award - Microsoft-internal 2023 MLADS conference
2022	David R. Cheriton Scholarship - 2-year award [20,000 CAD]
	Outstanding Reviewer - International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML'22)
2019	Best Poster Award - Cybersecurity and Privacy Institute (CPI) [1,000 CAD]
2018	Excellence Graduation - Master's degree
2016	KU Global Scholarship - Semester abroad, Korea University [1.2 million KRW]
2014	MOGAM Scholarship - Semester abroad, Yonsei University, Korea [3,000 EUR]

University Service

2022 Student Board Member - Cybersecurity and Privacy Institute (CPI)
School Advisory Committee on Appointments (SACA) Liaison - CrySP lab

Academic Service

Program Chair	RAID'24, CCS'23 (Artifact Evaluation)					
Session Chair	IEEE S&P'23					
External Reviewer	TheWebConf'24,	ICLR'24,	RAID'23,	PETS'23,	NeurIPS'23,	PETS'22,
	NeurIPS'22, ICML'22 (<i>Top 10%</i> ₹), PETS'21, CIKM'20					

Teaching

2018 | Data-Driven Medicine, Co-instructor at the RWTH-Aachen in Germany

Invited Talks

Dec, 2023	Analyzing Leakage of Personally Identifiable Information in Language Models,
	Meta, [slides]
Oct, 2023	How Reliable is Watermarking for Generative Machine Learning?
	University of California, Berkeley, [slides]
June, 2023	A Learnable Watermark for Deep Image Generators
	Google, [slides]
June, 2023	Analyzing Leakage of Personally Identifiable Information in Language Models
	MongoDB, [slides]